

SENIOR ENGINEER · RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE MANAGER · MACROECOLOGIST

🗷 erik.kusch@nhm.uio.no | R<sup>6</sup> Erik Kusch | 📵 0000-0002-4984-7646 | 🎢 www.erikkusch.com | 🎵 ErikKusch | 💆 KuschErik

## **Research Profile**

I am a macroecologist and data scientist specialised in streamlining work-flows, integration, and analysis of big data. My research uses quantitative tools to study ecosystem resilience, vegetation dynamics, and landscape-scale biodiversity to understand past, present, and future trajectories of ecosystems. My current work includes inference and analysis of ecological networks, simulation-based frameworks for ecological network inference assessments, and software development for climate data retrieval and aggregation.

## Education

### PhD in Biology; Specialisation on Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity

01/2020 - 04/2023

AARHUS UNIVERSITY (AU) & OXFORD UNIVERSITY (OX)

**Dissertation:** A Macroecological Perspective to Ecological Networks

#### M.Sc. in Biology; Specialisation on Biodiversity, Ecology and Evolution

08/2017 - 08/2019

University of Bergen (UIB) & Nansen Environmental and Remote Sensing Center (Nansen)

**Thesis:** Inferring Vegetation Memory From Remote Sensing Data And Identifying Causal Links To Plant Function

**B.Sc. in Biology** 10/2013 - 07/2017

TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD) & UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN (UIB)

Thesis: Remote Sensing And Predicting Shifts In Biome Distribution And Resilience Using NDVI Data

## **Specialised Training**

### Open, Reproducible, and Transparent Science in Ecology

Finse, Norway 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022

University of Bergen

7th Edition Species Distribution Modelling Course

Évora, Portugal

University of Évora, Science Retreats

26/04/2021 - 02/05/2021

**An Introduction to Bayesian Statistics** 

Glasgow, Scotland

University of Glasgow

06/04/2021 - 16/04/2021

Hierarchical Modelling of Species Communities with the R-package Hmsc

Helsinki, Finland

University of Helsinki

Modelling Challenges for Mountain Ecosystems

02/11/2020 - 06/11/2020

University of Hamburg

Hamburg, Germany 23/02/2020 - 28/02/2020

# **Experience**

### Senior Engineer / Research Infrastructure Manager

Oslo Norway

NATURAL HISTORY MUSEUM, UNIVERSITY OF OSLO

03/2023 - PRESENT

Research Fellow

Bergen, Norway

ECOLOGICAL AND ENVIRONMENTAL CHANGE RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

09/2019 - 12/2019

National Park Ranger & Environmental Education Guide

Saxony, Germany

NATIONAL PARK SAXON-BOHEMIAN SWISS

04/2016 - 06/2016

### **Research and Teaching Assistant**

BEHAVIOURAL ECOLOGY RESEARCH GROUP, UNIVERSITY OF LEIPZIG

08/2017 - 08/2019; 03/2017 - 04/2017

PRIMATE RESEARCH CENTRE, UNIVERSITY OF KYOTO

07/2018

1

GERMAN CENTRE FOR MARINE BIODIVERSITY RESEARCH, SENCKENBERG GROUP

05/2017 - 07/2017

#### **Student Assistant**

 ${\tt Botanical\ Institute, Technical\ University\ Dresden\ (TUD)}$ 

05/2016 - 08/2016; 02/2015 - 08/2015

ZOOLOGICAL COLLECTION, TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY DRESDEN (TUD)

04/2016 - 05/2016; 11/2013 - 08/2015

Teaching & Supervision Activity	
Bayesian Networks Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
AUTHOR & LECTURER	Ť
AU Bayes Study Group	Personal Course Web Page
AUTHOR & LECTURER	
Excursions into Biostatistics	© Course Web Page
AUTHOR & LECTURER	
An Introduction to Biostatistics Using R	© Course Web Page
AUTHOR & LECTURER	J
Biological Research in Theory and Praxis (BFTP)	© Course Web Page
Author	Aarhus University
Teaching Assistant	Aarhus University
APPLIED STATISTICS	22/03/2021 - 14/05/2021
STATISTICAL AND GEOSPATIAL MODELLING	03/09/2020 - 18/12/2020
GEOSPATIAL INFORMATION SYSTEMS	27/10/2020 - 18/12/2020
Instructor & Advisor	
ECOINFORMATICS & BIODIVERSITY MASTERS SEMINARS (EBMS), AARHUS UNIVERSITY	03/02/2021 - 05/05/2021
CENTRE OF EXCELLENCE IN BIODIVERSITY EDUCATION (BIOCEED), UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN	08/2017 - 07/2018
Talks & Workshops	
Climate Data with the KrigR Pipeline Workshop	Aarhus, Denmark
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, 5TH CONFERENCE OF NORDIC SOCIETY OIKOS 2022	07/07/2022
Ecological Network Inference - Pipedream or Pipeline	Oxford, England
Invited Speaker, SalGo Team, University of Oxford	22/05/2022
KrigR - The R Package	Hamburg, Germany
Speaker, AK Klima Interimstreffen	25/03/2021
KrigR - Downscaling State-of-the-Art Climate Data for Macroecologists	Aarhus, Denmark
AUTHOR & SPEAKER, BIOCHANGE METHODS WORKSHOPS	12/11/2020
KrigR - Climate Data For Your Spatial Study	
Invited Speaker, SalGo Team, University of Oxford	18/06/2020
SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020	25/06/2020
Identifying Ecological-Memory Patterns in Drylands using Remote Sensing	
Invited speaker, Ecosystem Research Group, University of Oxford	15/10/2019
SPEAKER, INTERNATIONAL SOCIETY FOR ECOLOGICAL MODELLING CONFERENCE 2019	04/10/2019
Invited speaker, Ecoinformatics and Biodiversity Research Group, University of Aarhus	06/09/2019
Spatial Patterns of Plant Performance	Bergen, Norway
Invited speaker, BIO Day, University of Bergen	15/03/2019
Inferring Vegetation Memory from Remote Sensing Data	Glasgow, Scotland
Invited speaker, Spatial Ecology Group, University of Glasgow	09/01/2019
Posters	
KrigR — Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data	London, England
Poster author and presenter, BES Climate Science for Ecological Forecasting Symposium 2022	11/05/2022
Intrinsic vegetation memory as a proxy of engineering resilience may be an	
oversimplification	05/00/0000
POSTER AUTHOR AND PRESENTER, INTERNATIONAL STATISTICAL ECOLOGY CONFERENCE 2020	25/06/2020
POSTER AUTHOR AND DESCRITER, RIFERVALES CENTRE FOR CLIMATE DESCRICH ANNUAL MEETING 2010	03/10/2019
Poster author and presenter, Bjerknes Centre for Climate Research Annual Meeting 2019	16/09/2019

# **Extracurricular Activity**

## **Group Member**

Statistics Journal Club, University of Glasgow	03/2021 - 03/2023
Spatial Shared-Interest Group, University of Glasgow	03/2021 - 03/2023
Bayes Study Group, University of Bergen	09/2018 - 12/2019
EECRG Reading Group, University of Bergen	10/2017 - 12/2019

**Leader & Dungeon Master** Aarhus, Denmark

AARHUS UNIVERSITY SECTION FOR ECOINFORMATICS DUNGEONS & DRAGONS GROUP 03/2022 - 01/2023

**Elected Member: Students Council of Biology Studies at the TUD** 

Dresden, Germany TECHNICAL UNIVERSITY OF DRESDEN 10/2013 - 10/2015

# Writing

## NetworkExtinction - an R package to simulate extinction's propagation and rewiring potential in ecological networks

M.Isidora Ávila-Thieme\*, **Erik Kusch**\*, Derek Corcoran\*, ..., Navarrete, Pablo A. Marquet

\* ... joint first-authorship; Rx Preprint - 2023

## A novel trophic cascade between cougars and feral donkeys shapes desert wetlands

ERICK LUNDGREN, DANIEL RAMP, OWEN MIDDLETON, EAMONN WOOSTER, ERIK KUSCH, [...], ARIAN WALLACH

### **MOSAIC: A Unified Trait Database to Complement Structured Population Models**

CONNOR BERNARD, GABRIEL SILVA SANTOS, [...], ERIK KUSCH, [...], ROBERTO SALGUERO-GÓMEZ

Rx Preprint - 2022

### Vegetation memory effects and their association with vegetation resilience in global drylands

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY, ALISTAIR SEDDON

**ᡂ** Journal of Ecology - 2022

### KrigR - A Tool for Downloading and Statistically Downscaling Climate Reanalysis Data

ERIK KUSCH, RICHARD DAVY

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2022

## Reconciling high resolution climate datasets using KrigR

RICHARD DAVY, ERIK KUSCH

6 Environmental Research Letters - 2021

## **Honours & Grants & Awards**

#### **SCHOLARSHIPS & GRANTS**

10/2020	<b>Scholarship for Academically Excellent Students</b> , Frands Christian Frantsen's Scholarship	Aarhus, Denmark
03/2019	Funding for Particularly Talented Students, Lina Asbjørnsens Stipendiefond	Bergen, Norway
02/2019	Fast-Track-Initiative Funding, FTI, Bjerknessenteret	Bergen, Norway
03/2018	<b>Project Grant</b> , L. Meltzers Høyskolefond	Bergen, Norway
2018/19	<b>Scholarship</b> , German Academic Scholarship Foundation (Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes)	Bonn, Germany

#### **AWARDS**

10/2019	<b>Best Poster: Student and Early Career Researcher</b> , International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria
10/2019	Modeller's Choice Poster Award, International Society for Ecological Modelling	Salzburg, Austria